Educational Opportunity Program (EOP); Records ua560
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Educational Opportunity Program (EOP) Records
1967-1986
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua560
.4 cubic ft.
The collection consists of inactive records from the University at Albany's Educational Opportunity Program (EOP).
Collection X
Biographical History
The Educational Opportunity Program (EOP) began in the summer of 1968 after a demand by the SUNYA Senate faculty and Black Student Alliance. The program represented a commitment to providing higher education opportunities for disadvantaged students with a motivation for college study. All those enrolled in the program were required to be residents of New York state, be educationally disadvantaged, and come from a low-income situation or live in a residence located in an area dominated by families with low incomes. Most students came from urban settings, with 60% from upstate and 40% from New York City. In the first year of operation, 160 students were enrolled. Funding originally came from the State of New York through SEEK appropriation. By September 1969, 370 students were enrolled in the program. Individual budgets were made for each student depending on their financial situation. EOP was focused on providing support services in three areas: academic, counseling, and financial services. Study and tutoring programs were available alongside reduced course loads. Counselors worked with the students as advisors on both personal and academic issues.
EOP continues to operate at the University at Albany under state and federal funding with a similar mission to provide academic services and support for economically or educationally disadvantaged students.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains inactive records related to the operation of the Educational Opportunity Program (EOP) at the University at Albany from 1967 to 1986. Correspondence, reports, handbooks and pamphlets, program information, plans, budgets/costs, surveys, staff and student information, memos, and more are included.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
State University of New York at Albany-Educational Opportunity Program (EOP); Universities and colleges -- New York (State) -- Albany -- Departments.; UAlbany Academic Administration; Education, Higher; State University of New York at Albany-Educational Opportunity Program (EOP)
- Letters to Campus News, 1967 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- EOP Records, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- EOP Records, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- EOP Records, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Interim Report on the Educational Opportunities Program, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- EOP Records, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Student Handbooks, ca. 1971; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- General EOP Meeting Flyer, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter to EOP Students, 1973 October 14 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- General Plan for 1973-1974, 1973 October 30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Tuition and Financial Aid Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 1976-1977 Budget Request, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- EOP Audit Report, 1979 May (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Class of 1981 Graduation Reception, 1981 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- EOP Records, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- EOP Records, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- EOP Records, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Entering Student Survey, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- 1969-1970 Grant Proposal, Higher Education Opportunity Program, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- 1975-1976 Preliminary Budget Request, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- 1982-1983 Financial Aid Information, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- EOP Pamphlets, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Itinerary, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)